Oliver Freud and Henny Fuchs Freud Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Oliver Freud and Henny Fuchs Freud Papers 1821-1993 (bulk 1907-1968)
MSS81384
Freud, Oliver, 1891-1969
Freud, Henny Fuchs, 1892-1971
8,000 items
14 containers
7 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Papers of Oliver Freud, photographer, engineer, and son of Sigmund Freud, and Henny Fuchs Freud, artist and wife of Oliver Freud. Correspondence, subject files, writings, photographs, and related material pertaining primarily to the emigration of family members from Austria and Europe during the Jewish holocaust. Also features a transcript of Oliver Freud’s recollection of his father, Sigmund Freud.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bernays, Anna Freud, 1858-1955--Correspondence.; Boaz family.; Bonaparte, Marie, Princess, 1882-1962--Correspondence.; Freud family.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982--Correspondence.; Freud, Ernst L., 1892-1970--Correspondence.; Freud, Eva Mathilde, 1924-1944.; Freud, Eva Mathilde, 1924-1944. Eva Mathilde Freud papers. 1924-1945.; Freud, Henny Fuchs, 1892-1971. Oliver and Henny Fuchs Freud papers. 1821-1968.; Freud, Martha, 1861-1951--Correspondence.; Freud, Oliver, 1891-1969.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939--Correspondence.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Hollitscher, Mathilde Freud, 1887-1978--Correspondence.; Kris, Marianne, 1900-1980--Correspondence.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945.
Places
Austria--Emigration and immigration.; Europe--Emigration and immigration.
Titles
Henny Fuchs Freud papers; Oliver Freud papers
Occupations
Artists.; Engineers.; Photographers.
Provenance
The papers of Oliver Freud, photographer, engineer, and son of Sigmund Freud, and Henny Fuchs Freud, artist, were given to the Library of Congress by Leli Freud in 1972 and by the Sigmund Freud Archives from circa 1952 to 1993. A letter by Oliver Freud to Marianne Kris was given by the Sigmund Freud Archives, Anton O. Kris, and Anna Kris Wolff in 2001. Some items donated by the Sigmund Freud Archives originally processed as part of the Sigmund Freud Papers have been transferred to this collection.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Oliver and Henny Fuchs Freud are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Oliver Freud
Date Event
1891, Feb. 19 Born, Vienna, Austria, son of Sigmund and Martha Bernays Freud
circa 1915 Graduated with degree in civil engineering from Vienna Technical Institute, Vienna, Austria
circa 1916 1918 Served in Austrian army, World War I
1920s Engineer, various firms, Berlin, Germany
1923 Married Henny Fuchs
circa 1933 1943 Worked as a commercial photographer in France
1943 Immigrated to United States
1943 1945 Taught mathematics, United States Army specialized training program
1945 1958 Engineer, Budd Co., Philadelphia, Pa.
1969, Jan. 24 Died, Williamstown, Mass.
Henny Fuchs Freud
Date Event
1892, Nov. 2 Born, Berlin, Germany
1920s Graduated from Charlotten Lyceum, Berlin, Germany Studied art under Lovis Corinth and graduated from State Academy of Fine Arts, Weimar, Germany Studied at academies of fine arts in Berlin and Dusseldorf, Germany Exhibited paintings at various shows in Germany and France
1923 Married Oliver Freud
1924 Birth of daughter, Eva Mathilde Freud (died in France, 1944)
circa 1933 1943 Lived in France
1943 Immigrated to the United States
1945 circa 1965 Exhibited artwork at various shows in the United States
1971, Apr. 30 Died, Williamstown, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Oliver Freud (1891-1969) and Henny Fuchs Freud (1892-1971) span the years 1821-1993, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1907-1968. Included are correspondence, subject files, writings, photographs, and related material. Early nineteenth-century material consisting of legal items and other documents pertains to the Boas (Boaz) family, ancestors of Henny Fuchs Freud. A small addition contains an account of the life of the Freud’s daughter, Eva Mathilde Freud, and a letter by Oliver Freud to Marianne Kris. The collection includes documents in German, French, and English.
Freud family material concerns Sigmund Freud and the dispersion and flight of various family members from Austria and then Europe during World War II. Correspondents include Anna Freud Bernays, Princess Marie Bonaparte, Anna Freud, Ernst L. Freud, Martha Bernays Freud, Sigmund Freud (photocopies only), and Mathilde Freud Hollitscher. The Eva Mathilde Freud series includes her correspondence and personal files before and after her parents' immigration to the United States. A transcript of an interview of Oliver Freud conducted in 1953 by K. R. Eissler includes Freud's recollection of his father.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Correspondence, 1907-1968
Subject File, 1821-1968
Eva Mathilde Freud Papers, 1924-1945
Writings, 1905-1968
Photographs, circa 1890-1968
Addition, 1939-1993
Container List
- Correspondence, 1907-1968 (Box 1-3)
  Letters sent and received by Oliver Freud and Henny Fuchs Freud, with attachments and related matter.
  Organized alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically therein.
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1946-1965 (Box 1)
  - Barbé, Robert-Henri, 1946-1967 (Box 1)
  - Bauersax, Hedda, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Bernays, Anna Freud, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Bernfeld, Siegfried, 1943-1946 (Box 1)
  - Bonaparte, Marie, Princess, 1920-1957, undated (Box 1)
  - Burlingham, Dorothy, 1967, undated (Box 1)
  - "B" miscellaneous, 1907-1967 (Box 1)
  - Caputo, Maria Elizabeth, 1933-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - "C" miscellaneous, 1945-1965 (Box 1)
  - De la Croix, Sister Alice Marie, 1941-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Dunst, Gertrud, 1938-1968 (Box 1)
  - "D-E" miscellaneous, 1913-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Fichtl, Paula, 1950, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Anna, 1945-1968 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Ernst L. and Lucie Brasch, 1962-1968 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Harry, 1947-1968 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Martha Bernays, 1941-1951 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Martin, 1959-1964 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Sigmund, photocopies of letters, 1924-1925, 1933, undated (Box 1)
  - Freud, W. Ernest, 1961-1967 (Box 2)
  - Fuchs, Gertrud and Paul, 1939-1942 (Box 2)
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1923-1964 (Box 2)
  - Girault, Chanoine, 1945-1967 (Box 2)
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1935-1966, undated (Box 2)
  - Hollitscher, Mathilde Freud, 1951-1968 (Box 2)
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1907-1968 (Box 2)
  - Irwin, Marian, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Israel, Rita,. 1950-1968, undated (Box 2)
  - Jakaitis, Edmund, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Johnke, E. D., 1945-1967, undated (Box 2)
  - Jones, Ernest, 1953-1958 (Box 2)
  - Joske, Henri, 1945-1966 (Box 2)
  - Katz, Rita, 1945-1966, undated (Box 2)
  - Koch, Friedrich Wilhelm, 1951, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Koch, Louise, 1946-1960, undated (Box 2)
  - "K" miscellaneous, 1945-1968, undated (Box 2)
  - Laser, Rodolfo, 1940-1968, undated (Box 2)
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1941-1968 (Box 2)
  - Marlé, Arnold and Lilly Freud, 1959-1966, undated (Box 2)
  - Mauthner, Margarete, 1937-1946 (Box 2)
  - Mazel, Vladimir, 1945-1967, undated (Box 2)
  - "M-O" miscellaneous, 1942-1967, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Pillon, L., 1945-1946, undated (Box 3)
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1945-1964, undated (Box 3)
  - Rosenbaum, Adele, 1945-1968, undated (Box 3)
  - Roth, Margaret, 1944-1968 (Box 3)
  - "R" miscellaneous, 1925-1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Sachs, Heide, 1947-1951, undated (Box 3)
  - "S-T" miscellaneous, 1945-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Vayana, Dorothy, 1958-1961 (Box 3)
  - Wertheim, Martha and Ernest, 1943-1946 (Box 3)
  - Wolfradt, Marianne, Nana, and Willi, 1936-1968, undated (Box 3)
  - "W" miscellaneous, 1946-1968, undated (Box 3)
  - Yoast, Bertha, undated (Box 3)
  - Unidentified (Box 3)
    - From Oliver Freud, 1956 (Box 3)
    - To Oliver and Henny Fuchs Freud, 1938-1968, undated (Box 3)
- Subject File, 1821-1968 (Box 3-8)
  Correspondence, reports, family memorabilia, financial matter, legal data, lists, recollections, journals, and miscellaneous material.
  Organized alphabetically by subject or topic and chronologically therein.
  - Adoption plans by Oliver and Henny Fuchs Freud, 1945-1947 (Box 3)
  - Art and art exhibits by Henny Fuchs Freud and others, 1958-1967, undated (Box 3)
  - Biographical material Freud, Henny Fuchs, 1948-1967, undated (Box 3)
  - Freud, Oliver, 1943-1963, undated (Box 3)
  - Boas, Samuel, medical career, 1821-1875 (Box 3)
  - Boas family, 1830-1927, undated (Box 4)
  - Budd Co., 1950-1967, undated (Box 4)
  - Christmas cards, 1966, undated (Box 4)
  - Class notes and related material (Box 4)
    - Freud, Henny Fuchs Art, 1954-1962, undated (Box 4)
      - French, 1946-1962, undated (Box 4)
      - German, 1960, undated (Box 4)
    - Freud, Oliver Freud, 1943-1967 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence lists, 1962-1964 (Box 4)
  - Financial (Box 4)
    - Cancelled checks (Box 4)
      - 1957-1961, (3 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1962-1964, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Checkbooks, 1958-1964 (Box 5)
    - Claims for compensation from the West German government by Henny Fuchs Freud and her sisters, 1956-1968, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - General, 1941-1967 (Box 5)
    - Income tax, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - Williamstown, Mass., house, 1963-1964, undated (Box 5)
  - France, flight from, 1943, undated (Box 5)
  - Freud, Sigmund, transcript of interview containing Oliver Freud’s recollections of his father, 1953 (Box 5)
  - Fuchs, Paul and wife (parents of Henny Fuchs Freud), efforts to locate, 1942-1943 (Box 5)
  - Furniture, designs for, undated Genealogical charts, Henny Fuchs Freud, father's family, 1939 (Box 5)
  - Green River, Mass., improvement project, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
  - Guest book, 1943-1968 (Box 6)
  - Health of Henny Fuchs Freud, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Legal documents, birth certificates, wills, and identification papers, 1891-1965 (Box 6)
  - Market study by Henny Fuchs Freud for advertising children's furniture for firm of Schwartz and Fröhlich, 1932 (Box 5)
  - Marriage of Oliver and Henny Fuchs Freud, program, 1923 (Box 6)
  - Mezuzah, undated Mileage journals of Oliver Freud, 1948-1965 (Box 6)
  - National League of American Pen Women, 1950-1968, undated (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 6)
    - American, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - French (Box 7)
    - German (Box 7)
    - Israeli (Box 7)
  - Photographs, lists of, 1955 (Box 7)
  - Printed matter, 1939-1968, undated, (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - Prints and drawings, 1950, undated (Box 7)
  - Teaching positions sought by Oliver and Henny Fuchs Freud, 1944-1965 (Box 7)
  - Miscellany, 1920, 1967, undated (Box 8)
- Eva Mathilde Freud Papers, 1924-1945 (Box 8)
  Correspondence, subject files, and writings pertaining to Eva Mathilde Freud, daughter of Oliver and Henny Fuchs Freud.
  Organized alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Arthaud, Reine, 1941-1943, undated (Box 8)
    - Doujette, 1939, undated (Box 8)
    - Dub, Hélène, 1942-1943, undated (Box 8)
    - Freud, Oliver and Henny Fuchs, 1942-1943 (Box 8)
    - "H-M" miscellaneous, 1931-1944, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Olliver, Henriette, 1943 (Box 8)
    - "P-R" miscellaneous, 1941-1943, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Schwab, Andree, 1941 (Box 8)
    - Wolfradt, Marianne, undated undated (Box 8)
    - Unidentified to Eva Mathilde Freud, 1942-1943, undated (Box 8)
  - Subject file (Box 8)
    - Baby books, 1924-1925 (Box 8)
    - Death, 1944-1945 (Box 8)
    - Employment, 1943-1944 (Box 8)
    - Financial, 1941-1944 (Box 8)
    - Legal documents, 1942-1943 (Box 8)
    - Lycée, 1934-1941, undated (Box 8)
    - Medical, 1942-1944 (Box 8)
    - Miscellany, 1929, 1942, undated (Box 8)
    - Université, 1941-1943 (Box 8)
  - Writings (Box 8)
    - By Eva Mathilde Freud, 1931, undated (Box 8)
    - By others, undated (Box 8)
- Writings, 1905-1968 (Box 9)
  Typed and handwritten manuscripts of articles, speeches, and other presentations by Oliver Freud and Henny Fuchs Freud.
  Organized alphabetically by name of author and chronologically therein
  - Freud, Henny Fuchs (Box 9)
    - Birthday poem to her father, Paul Fuchs, undated (Box 9)
    - Poem to her parents for their wedding anniversary, 1905 (Box 9)
    - Talks on France, circa 1944 (Box 9)
    - Trip journal, 1956, 1961 (Box 9)
  - Freud, Oliver (Box 9)
    - "Exodus 1942/43," 1968 (Box 9)
    - "Exodus 1943," 1968 (Box 9)
    - "Memories of World War I, 1914-1918," 1953 (Box 9)
    - "The Nationality Problem in Europe," 1944 (Box 9)
    - Short stories, undated (Box 9)
    - Speech on exodus from France, 1951 Others, 1951-1967, undated (Box 9)
  - Others, 1951-1967, undated (Box 9)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1968 (Box 9-14)
  Family and other photographs.
  Unarranged.
  - circa 1890-1968, (2 folders); (6 folders); (5 folders); (3 folders) (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
- Addition, 1939-1993 (Box 14)
  An account of the life and death of Eva Mathilde Freud by Pierre Segond, typewritten transcripts of two letters by her, and a letter by Oliver Freud to Marianne Kris.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - "Eva Freud: One Life," by Pierre Segond, including a French version and typewritten transcripts of two letters by Eva Mathilde Freud (1939 and 1944), 1992-1993 (Box 14)
  - Letter from Oliver Freud to Marianne Kris, 1950 (Box 14)